Guide to the Elizabeth Jenks Clark Collection of Margaret Anderson
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Elizabeth Jenks Clark Collection of Margaret Anderson
1914-1998
1945-1973
YCAL MSS 265
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
17.71
(32 boxes)
The Elizabeth Jenks Clark Collection of Margaret Anderson contains correspondence, writings, photographs, sound recordings, and other papers of and concerning writer and editor Margaret Anderson. The material documents Anderson's life, work and personal relationships with many noted writers, poets, artists, photographers and performers of the twentieth century, including her close friendships with sculptor Elizabeth Jenks Clark and writer Solita Solano. The papers span the years 1886 to 1998.
Anderson, Margaret C., 1886-1973
Clark, Elizabeth Jenks
Hills, Mathilda M.
Solano, Solita, 1888-1975
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Mathilda M. Hills on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, 2004. Gift of Mathilda M. Hills, 2004 and 2006.
Custodial History
Elizabeth Jenks Clark collection of Margaret Anderson contains material of mixed provenance. After Anderson's death, Elizabeth Jenks Clark and Solita Solano inherited her papers. Following the death of Solano, Clark lived with Mathilda Hills, who inherited Anderson's and Clark's papers when Clark died.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
‡3 Boxes 30-32: ‡a Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult Access Services. Preservation photocopies, photographic prints, and access copies of sound recordings for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm service copy (film number 2750) is available for Series II. Writings, The Unknowable Gurdjieff, Solita Solano, notes on Georges Ivanovitch Gurdjieff; and Other notes.
Margaret Anderson (1886-1973)
Margaret Anderson was born November 24, 1886 in Indianapolis, Indiana to Arthur Aubrey Anderson and Jessie Shortridge Anderson. The eldest of three daughters, she attended high school in Anderson, Indiana and attended a two-year junior preparatory class at Western College for Women in Oxford, Ohio. Increasingly drawn to music, Anderson left college to pursue a career as a pianist. In the fall of 1908, she left Indiana and moved to Chicago with her sister Lois, where she reviewed books for The Continent until she joined the staff of The Dial. By 1913 she was also a book critic for the Chicago Evening Post, which at that time shared a building with The Dial. According to Anderson, during that time she learned monotype, linotype and proofreading at The Dial. Bored at the Chicago Evening Post, she decided to edit her own magazine, giving it the title of Little Review. The Little Review was launched as a monthly publication in March of 1914. Anderson's main goal was to publish creative criticism.
In 1916, Margaret Anderson met Jane Heap. Heap was born in Topeka, Kansas and moved to Chicago to attend the Art Institute of Chicago, eventually becoming an art teacher at the Lewis Institute. Soon after the two women met, they fell in love and moved in together. Heap joined Anderson as co-editor of the Little Review, maintaining a low profile by using a number of pseudonyms, such as "R" and "Garnerin" and usually signing pieces just "jh," but she had an enormous influence. After briefly moving the magazine to Mill Valley, California, Anderson and Heap then moved it to New York City in 1917 with the help of critic Ezra Pound, who the same year started his two-year tenure as foreign editor of the Little Review in London. Pound's contribution to the magazine was profound since he had strong relationships with many European experimental writers, and he informed the direction of the magazine until its end. The Little Review 's opinion on current art and literature was influential and the magazine stated opinions frankly; in 1916 Anderson and Heap printed an issue entirely of blank pages, a statement on the quality of the current submissions. Total editorial control was important to Anderson and Heap: they were careful to not accept financial support in fear that the supporters' opinions would affect the content. In 1918, Pound sent parts of James Joyce's Ulysses to Anderson and Heap and the Little Review began publishing excerpts of the manuscript. In 1920, at half-way through the novel, the United States Post Office seized and burned issues of the magazine, charging it obscene. In 1921 a court convicted Anderson and Heap on obscenity charges and fined each woman fifty dollars. The trial garnered a great deal of publicity for all parties involved.
The Little Review then began a period of decline, Anderson turned over the editorship of the magazine to Heap in 1923 and moved to Paris. The Little Review began quarterly publication in 1923 due to diminishing funds, and by 1926 it was published sporadically until its suspension the same year. One final issue was published from Paris in 1929. By the time it was finished, the Little Review had published some of the most influential new writers in the English language, including T.S. Eliot, Hart Crane, Ernest Hemingway, Sherwood Anderson, Andre Breton, Jean Cocteau, Marcel Duchamp, Emma Goldman, Amy Lowell, Juan Gris, Fernand Leger, Remy de Gourmont, Wallace Stevens, Arthur Waley, and William Carlos Williams.
Anderson and Heap lived together for seven years, though their romantic relationship became strained. Anderson had an affair with Gladys Tilden, causing further turmoil between her and Heap. In 1923, Anderson met and fell in love with the French singer Georgette Leblanc, former companion and accompanist of Maurice Maeterlinck, and moved to Paris with Leblanc. Heap moved to Paris the same year and that summer Anderson's sister Lois Karinsky fell ill, prompting Heap and Anderson to co-adopt Anderson's nephews, Tom and Fritz Peters. In 1929, Anderson met and started an affair with Solita Solano, a poet and the partner of Janet Flanner. Anderson lived happily with Leblanc, whom Anderson considered to be her great love, and continued her affair with Solano for several years. Anderson wrote and studied piano in Le Cannet until Leblanc's death of cancer in 1941. Grief-stricken and seeking the solace of friends, Anderson boarded the S.S. Drottningholm for the United States. On board she met and fell in love with Dorothy Caruso, widow of the singer Enrico Caruso, who was also returning to the United States from France. Within days of arriving back in the Unites States, Anderson befriended Elizabeth Jenks Clark through Solano, who had returned and was living in the U.S. Clark and Solano became Anderson's closest friends and she corresponded with them almost daily until her death. Anderson and Caruso lived together in New York until Caruso's death in 1955. Clark and Solano moved to Orgeval, France, prompting Anderson, who was mourning the loss of Caruso, to return to Le Cannet. Anderson lived out the remainder of her years in Le Cannet, until she fell ill of emphysema in 1973 and entered the Clinique Beausoleil in Cannes. She died on October 19, 1973 of heart failure and was buried beside Georgette Leblanc in the Notre Dame des Agnes Cemetery.
The teachings of George Ivanovitch Gurdjieff played a profound role in Anderson's life. While in Paris, Anderson became close to Gurdjieff, an eastern philosopher and spiritual teacher who fled post-czarist Russia and whose philosophies promoted self-transformation through development and awakening. Anderson and Leblanc studied with him, focusing on his original teaching called The Fourth Way, which combined simultaneously focusing on body, mind and emotions to achieve higher levels of consciousness. From October 1935 through the summer of 1939, eight women studying with Gurdjieff comprised the core of a group of women known as The Rope: Margaret C. Anderson, Jane Heap, Georgette Leblanc, Solita Solano, Kathryn Hulme, Louise Davidson, Elizabeth Gordon, and Alice Rohrer. The Rope was most active from 1936 to 1938. Heap became a lifelong student and teacher of Gurdjieff's work, moving to London where she led Gurdjieff study groups until her death in 1964. Anderson remained a student of Gurdjieff's until his death in October 1949, writing about him and his teachings in most of her books, most thoroughly in The Unknowable Gurdjieff, which she dedicated to Heap.
Over thirty-two years, Anderson published a three-volume autobiography: My Thirty Years' War, The Fiery Fountains, and The Strange Necessity. The final volume was dedicated to Solano, who served as a critic throughout the book's creation. In her last years in Le Cannet, she wrote her final book, part novel and part memoir, Forbidden Fires, which recounts her days with Georgette Leblanc and Jane Heap. The book was published in 1996 through the efforts of Mathilda Hills, a University of Rhode Island professor who lived with Elizabeth Jenks Clark and edited the manuscript.
Chronology of Events in Margaret Anderson's Life
1886 Born November 24 in Indianapolis, Indiana.
1908 Moved to Chicago, reviewed books for The Continent, The Dial, and the Chicago Evening Post
1914 In March, edited and published the first Little Review.
1916 Met Jane Heap.
1917 Moved the Little Review to New York.
1918 The Little Review began serially publishing James Joyce's Ulysses. Anderson met Gladys Tilden.
1920 The United State Post Office seized and burned issues of the magazine, charging Anderson and Heap with obscenity.
1921 Convicted with Heap of obscenity.
1923 Attended lectures by George Ivanovitch Gurdjieff. Moved to Le Cannet. Moved to Paris with Leblanc. Met Georgette Leblanc, ended her romantic relationship with Heap and turned over editorship of the Little Review.
1923 Heap moved to Paris. Heap and Anderson co-adopted Anderson's nephews.
1926 The Little Review suspended publication.
1929 Final issue of the Little Review published. Anderson met Solita Solano.
1930 My Thirty Years' War published.
1932 Anderson and Leblanc lived temporarily in Vernet and began studies with Gurdjieff in Paris.
1933 Anderson and Solano ended their affair.
1935-1939 The Rope was active.
1941 Leblanc died.
1942 Anderson returned to the United States. Met Dorothy Caruso.
1949 Gurdjieff died.
1951 The Fiery Fountains published.
1955 Caruso died.
1959 Anderson returned to Le Cannet.
1962 The Strange Necessity and The Unknowable Gurdjieff published.
1964 Heap died.
1973 October 19, Anderson died of heart failure in Cannes.
Elizabeth Jenks Clark
Elizabeth Jenks Clark (1912-1989) was born Elizabeth Story Jenks in Narragansett, Rhode Island. During her childhood, the family lived in Mount Kemble, Morristown, New Jersey and spent their summers at Anawan Cliffs in Narragansett. Clark, known as "Lib" among family and friends, graduated from Miss Porter's School and completed her education in Paris. In 1928, she married Joseph P. Clark, a future two-term United States Senator, and together they had a son, Joseph Clark, Jr. She and her husband separated in 1931 and Elizabeth moved to Paris while the divorce was finalized. While in Paris, Clark sculpted a fish fountain for the town of Narragansett at the studio of sculptor Janet Scudder. For the rest of the 1930s Clark lived and sculpted in Philadelphia and New York City while she raised her son. In 1941, she joined the American Women's Voluntary Service (A.W.V.S.), for which she organized branches throughout the United States. While in New York City, Clark met and fell in love with a fellow member of the A.W.V.S., poet and editor Sarah Wilkinson, also known as Solita Solano. Solano, a poet and the partner of Janet Flanner, had recently repatriated from France. Though Clark and Solano would live together for the rest of Solano's life, Solano maintained a close bond with Flanner.
Through Solano, Clark met Margaret Anderson in New York City in July of 1942. Clark, Solano and Anderson would remain close and loyal friends until Anderson's death in 1973. After the war, Clark worked in New York City at the Fifth Avenue boutique Henri Bendel and at the fashion house of designer Mainbocher. In the late 1940s, she and Solano moved to Arizona and California to be near family and friends. When Clark's parents' health began to fail in the early 1950s, Clark and Solano moved to the Jenks family's Mount Kemble property and lived there until 1958, when the two women moved to Orgeval, France. Solano died in 1975 and was buried in Orgeval. Clark returned to live in the United States in November of 1976 and settled in Kingston, RI. From 1979 until her death from cancer in 1989, Clark shared her life with Mathilda Hills, a member of the English faculty at the University of Rhode Island. Mathilda Hills edited and made possible the publication of Forbidden Fires, Margaret Anderson's last book.
Scope and Contents
The Elizabeth Jenks Clark Collection of Margaret Anderson contains correspondence, writings, photographs, sound recordings, and other papers of writer and editor Margaret Anderson. The material documents Anderson's life, work, and personal relationships with many noted writers, poets, artists, photographers and performers of the twentieth century, in particular her romantic relationships with co-editor and writer Jane Heap, writer Solita Solano and close friendship with sculptor Elizabeth Jenks Clark. The papers span the entirety of Anderson's life, though the bulk of them document her personal and professional life after the Little Review. The papers are a unique resource on Anderson's personal life in France, including her friendship and studies with George Ivanovitch Gurdjieff and participation in The Rope. A portion of the papers also document publishing the Little Review and provide context for Anderson's role as founder and editor of the magazine.
Correspondence, writings and photographs comprise the bulk of the papers. Personal correspondence illuminates Anderson's close friendships, romantic relationships and professional pursuits. Letters between Anderson and her friends, namely Clark, Solano, Jane Heap, Dorothy Caruso, Georgette Leblanc, Janet Flanner, and Kathryn Hulme, reveal not only the deep love and friendship among the women but also capture the experience of their lesbian relationships through the middle of the twentieth century. Correspondence regarding Anderson's writings reveal her creative process and the criticism that she sought and rejected from her friends, including publisher Coburn Britton. Correspondence is throughout the first and second series.
Anderson's writings include drafts for books and other writings and are heavily annotated, often including notes by Anderson and Solano, who acted as editor for much of her work. Photographs include portraits that appeared in the Little Review and snapshots of friends and family. Writings by others include poems by Solita Solano and Georgette Leblanc and a collection of humorous drawings by Leblanc. Also included is a draft of Anderson and Solano's English translation of Leblanc's memoir Souvenirs: My Life with Maeterlinck. Sound recordings include interviews with Anderson's family and friends. Anderson's personal papers and Mathilda Hill's research material on Anderson make up the smallest portion of the papers. Mathilda Hills's holograph notes describing Anderson's papers can be found throughout the collection.
Arrangement
The Elizabeth Jenks Clark Collection of Margaret Anderson is organized into seven series: General Correspondence, Writings, Writings of Others, Photographs, Sound Recordings, Personal Papers, and Mathilda Hills Papers.
Little review (Chicago, Ill.); American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors -- 20th Century; Lesbians; Lesbian authors; Poets -- 2 20th century; Publishers and publishing; Women authors; Audiovisual materials; Photographs; Sound recordings; Authors; Editors; LGBTQ resource; Man Ray, 1890-1976; Abbott, Berenice, 1898-1991; Anderson, Margaret C., 1886-1973; Britton, Coburn; Caruso, Dorothy, 1893-1955; Clark, Elizabeth Jenks; Davidson, Louise; George, Victor; Gurdjieff, Georges Ivanovitch, 1872-1949; Heap, Jane, 1883-1964; Hills, Mathilda M.; Hulme, Kathryn, 1900-1981; Leblanc, Georgette, 1869-1941; Solano, Solita, 1888-1975
- General Correspondence, 1932-1981, undated; Series I; 4.17; (10 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I, General Correspondence is organized into two subseries: Margaret Anderson Correspondence and Third Party Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  Margaret Anderson Correspondence contains correspondence between Anderson and colleagues and friends. The letters discuss Anderson's personal life, her writings, and recollections of her work as editor of the Little Review and her studies with Georges Ivanovitch Gurdjieff. Interfiled among the correspondence are Anderson's letter drafts and notes.
  There is extensive correspondence with Elizabeth Jenks Clark and Solita Solano. Until 1965, most letters were sent to Clark with an occasional letter to both. After 1965, nearly all letters are addressed to both women. These letters discuss Anderson's writings and their publication process and the personal life of Anderson and friends. Commonly, Anderson typed and then added holograph notes to the letter. Upon receipt, Clark and Solano would add holograph notes. Additional correspondence with Clark and Solano is in Series II, Writings.
  Anderson's correspondence with Jane Heap documents their work together on the Little Review, their romantic relationship, and later their friendship and co-adoption of Anderson's nephews. Letters with Coburn Britton, the publisher of Anderson's three-volume autobiography, document Anderson's writing process and includes draft fragments.
  Margaret Anderson's personal and professional life is also documented through her correspondence with prominent figures such as Emma Goldman, Kathryn Hulme, Edmund Wilson, Georgette Leblanc, Virgil Thomson, Maurice Maeterlinck, and Alice B. Toklas. Letters from Emma Goldman include an account of the death of Alexander "Sasha" Berkman. A letter to Jackie Porter is accompanied by Margaret Anderson's 1967 prepared but unused suicide note to friends.
  Nicknames given to various friends by George Ivanovitch Gurdjieff are used among some correspondents: Anderson was Yakina; Kathryn Hulme was Krokodeel or Crocodile; Solita Solano was Kanari or Canary; and Alice Ruhrer was "Theen One" or Boa Constrictor. Nicknames not coined by Gurdjieff also appear throughout the correspondence: "Martie" is Anderson; "Tippy" is Josephine Plowsday; "Coby" is Coburn Britton; and Allen Tanner is "Narcisse."
  Third Party Correspondence contains correspondence primarily to Elizabeth Jenks Clark, Mathilda Hills and Solita Solano and includes a small amount of correspondence to other individuals. Notable correspondents include T.S. Eliot, Gertrude Stein, Vera Nabokov, Sybille Bedford, Nancy Cunard, Daphne Fielding, Janet Flanner, Kathryn Hulme, and Moura Lympany.
  Additional correspondence is located in Series II, Writings. Cross references have been provided between this series and Series II for all correspondence with Anderson. Cross references have not been provided for Elizabeth Jenks Clark and Solita Solano because of the volume of their correspondence throughout both series.
  - Margaret Anderson
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. A small amount of unidentified correspondence, notes and correspondence drafts, and correspondence regarding permission is filed at the end of the subseries.
    - Ambler, Hilton, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Anderson Family, 1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Includes letters from Lois Karinsky
    - Aude, Odette, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Barker, Bee, 1973 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Boda, ___, 1973 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Boston University, 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Boyle, Kay, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes photographs of Georges Ivanovitch Gurdjieff, Margaret Anderson, and unidentified
    - Brialix, ___, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Britton, Coburn, 1969-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 9-12)
      Includes draft fragments and letter to Janet Flanner from Anderson
      General note
      See also:Britton, Coburn
    - Bryer, Jackson, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Caruso, Dorothy, 1947-1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Caruso, Gloria, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes her writings and "Little Poems of our Days"
    - Champcommunal, Elspeth, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Clark, Elizabeth Jenks, 1956-1957, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    - Clark, Elizabeth Jenks; Solano, Solita, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
      Includes letter from Luba Gurdjieff to Dorothy Caruso
    - Clark, Elizabeth Jenks; Solano, Solita, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 22-37)
      Includes 1934 poems by Georgette Leblanc
    - Clark, Elizabeth Jenks; Solano, Solita, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 38-51)
    - Clark, Elizabeth Jenks; Solano, Solita, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 52-61)
    - Clark, Elizabeth Jenks; Solano, Solita, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 62-72)
      Includes photographs of Orgeval residence, writings and materials regarding Margaret Anderson's death
    - Clark, Elizabeth Jenks; Solano, Solita, 1973, undated (Box 6, Folder 73-74)
    - Codman, Florence, 1969, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Dale, Ernest, 1969 March 26 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Davidson, Louise, 1940-1969 (Box 6, Folder 77)
      Includes photograph of Margaret Anderson and unidentified person in Orgeval.
      See also: Heap, Jane
    - Davis, Betty Lou, 1971, undated (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - de Larroche, Alicia, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - de Salzmann, Jeanne, 1951 January 3 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Downs, Betty, 1971 January 19 (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Fetherling, Doug, 1972 August 19 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - Fielding, Daphne, 1970-1971, undated (Box 6, Folder 83)
      See also:Fielding, Daphne
    - Ford, Hugh, 1967-1972 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Goddard, Gladys, 1945-1948, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 85)
      Includes photograph of Gloria Goddard and Gladys Goddard
    - Goldman, Emma, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 86)
      Letter of conveyance for carbons of Goldman's outgoing letters regarding death of Alexander Berkman to John Foyse, Reginald Wright Kauffman of the Washington Post, and unidentified recipient
    - Gotham Book Mart
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Steloff, Frances
    - Gotlieb, Howard
      See: Boston University
    - Hamilton, Charles, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - Heap, Jane, circa 1918-1944, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 88-95)
      Includes photographs dated 1939; drawings of Margaret Anderson; some letters are also addressed to Elspeth Champcommunal; includes letters from Margaret Anderson to Solita Solano and from Solita Solano to Jane Heap.
    - Heitz, Helen, circa 1974 (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - Herald-Tribune, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 97)
      Regards Love Story by Erich Segal and includes clippings
    - Houghton Library, Harvard University, 1967 October 23 (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - Huckle, Dorothea, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 99)
    - Hulme, Kathryn, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 100)
    - Hunter, Bruce, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 101)
    - Karinsky, Lois Anderson, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - Karinsky, Mary
      See: Palmer, Jean Anderson and Mary Karinsky
    - Kazin, Alfred, 1970, undated (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1949, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - Krakower, Diane, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - [Kramer], Agnes, undated (Box 7, Folder 106)
    - Kramer, Dorothy, 1973 September 28 (Box 7, Folder 107)
      Includes itinerary, June-August 1973
    - Kramer, Kent, 1969 March 21 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - Landaner, Madeleine, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - Lank, Thomas, 1970 August 28 (Box 7, Folder 110)
    - Lauterstein and Lauterstein